Guide to the Broadus Bailey French Revolution print collection, 1804
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
Broadus Bailey French Revolution print collection
1804
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
Broadus Bailey
C0072
1.5 linear ft.; 1 box
Print engravings of the French Revolution by Pierre-Gabriel Berthault (1737-1831). Berthault created the engravings from drawings by Jean-Louis Prieur (1759-1795). These images begin with the Estates General meeting before the Revolution officially begins and continues through until just after King Louis XVI is executed. The images measure approximately 18x24cm to 18x26cm.
Administrative Information
Alternative Form Available
The entire collection is available online through the.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Broadus Bailey in January 2010.
Historical Information
The French Revolution began in June 1789 when the Estates-General signed the Tennis Court Oath, pledging to write a constitution. The king worried about their goals and safety, so he sent in the military to keep the peace. On July 11, 1789, King Louis XVI fired his finance minister, Jacques Necker, a favorite of the people. The people thought this meant a coup against the Assembly and began an open rebellion on July 12. On July 14, a Parisian mob stormed the Bastille fortress, a symbol of monarchical tyranny; they killed the governor, Launay, after the cease-fire and paraded his head around on a pike. The turmoil continued until the king went to Paris on July 17 to show his support.
While the National Assembly worked on a new constitution, the economic conditions in France, especially Paris, worsened. Women gathered in the market on October 5 and marched to city hall to have their demands heard. Not happy with the city officials' responses, the women marched to Versailles to see the king. To help calm the women, Lafayette convinced the king to move to Paris with his family. Over the course of the next two years, the National Assembly worked on a constitution. During this time, different factions struggled for power. Just before the constitution was finished in the summer of 1791, the king and his family tried to flee France. They were discovered in Varennes and returned to Paris, where he was forced to agree to a constitutional monarchy.
In another year, another faction would rise to power, abolish the monarchy, and declare a Republic. The new Republic declared a war on Austria and counter-revolutionaries led a resistance movement to the new government. Louis XVI and his family was arrested and Louis and Marie-Antoinette were executed, along with about 40,000 people during the Reign of Terror. The Thermidorian Reaction led to the arrest of Robespierre and an end to the terror. A new constitution was accepted and established the directory. This government saw the end of the revolution and the rise of Napoleon.
Jean-Louis Prieur, called the Young, was born in Paris in 1759 to a sculptor, designer, and engraver. An artist himself, Prieur the Young made more than sixty drawings of episodes of the Revolution, beginning with the unrest before the taking of the Bastille. He was arrested in Year III of the revolution and guillotined in 1795.
Pierre-Gabriel Berthault was born in 1737 and became an engraver. His greatest work was his cooperation with the "Tableaux Historiques". His name appears on over one hundred prints. He was called away to run a printing workshop for the Republic where he oversaw the formidable publication of "Description de l'Égypte". He died in 1831 in Paris.
Scope and Content
Print engravings of the French Revolution by Pierre-Gabriel Berthault (1737-1831). Berthault created the engravings from drawings by Jean-Louis Prieur (1759-1795). These images begin with the Estates General meeting before the Revolution officially begins and continues through until just after King Louis XVI is executed. Many of the prints illustrate pillaging, massacres, fighting, and important events in the Revolution, such as the taking of the Bastille, Louis moving his family to the Tuileries Palace, Louis XVI's flight to Varennes, and the execution of the King. Many of the key figures of the Revolution to this time can be found in several of the images, including Jacques Necker, King Louis XVI, Lafayette, Mirabeau, Marquis de Favras, and the Marquis de Launey. Some of the 82 prints appear to have been created by an artist other than Berthault, or perhaps appeared in a publication other than "Tableaux Historiques". The images measure approximately 18x24cm to 18x26cm.
Arrangement
Organized according to numbers found on the images.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
.
Index Terms
Geographical Names:
France--History--Revolution, 1789-1799.
Document Types:
Engravings.
Contents List
- Series 1: Engravings, 1789-1793
  Engravings, mostly copperplate, from "Collection complete des tableaux historiques de la revolution francaise". These were engraved by Pierre-Gabriel Berthault (1737-1831) after drawings by Jean-Louis Prieur (1759-1795).
  - Le peuple déliverant les gardes françaises a l'Abbaye St. Germain, June 30, 1789 (Box 1, Page 2)
    The people deliver the French guards to the Abby St. Germain.
  - Motion faite au Palais Royal, par Camille Desmoulins, July 12, 1789 (Box 1, Page 3)
    Motion made at the Palais Royal, by Camille Desmoulins.
  - Le peuple faisant fermer l'Opéra, July 12, 1789 (Box 1, Page 4)
    The people working to close the Opera.
  - Les gardes françaises sauvant Mr. Du Chatelet, leur colonel, de l'effervescence populaire, July 12, 1789 (Box 1, Page 5)
    The French guards saving Mr. Du Chatelet, their colonel, from popular turmoil.
  - Les bustes de Mrs. d'Orléans et Necker portés a la Place Louis XV, July 12, 1789 (Box 1, Page 6)
    The busts of Madame Orléans and Necker carried to the Place Louis XV.
  - Incendie du corps de garde sur le Pont Neuf, August 29, 1788 (Box 1, Page 6)
    Burning of the guardhouse on the Pont Neuf.
  - Mr. de Lambesc entrant aux Tuileries, avec un détachement de Royal-Allemand, July 12, 1789 (Box 1, Page 7)
    Mr. Lambesc entering the Tuileries with a detachment of the Royal German army.
  - Action entre Royal-Allemand et un détachement des gardes françaises, en face du dépot, July 12, 1789 (Box 1, Page 8)
    Action between Royal German guards and a detachment of French guards, across from the depot.
  - Fusillade au Fauxbourg Antoine, April 28, 1789 (Box 1, Page 9)
    **This one looks different from the rest and has a paragraph explanation to go with it; different artist too** Gunfire at Fauxbourg Antoine.
  - Les troupes du Champ de Mars partant pour la Place Louis XV, July 12, 1789 (Box 1, Page 9)
    Troops of the Champ de Mars leaving for the Place Louis XV.
  - Barriere de la conférence incendiée, July 12, 1789 (Box 1, Page 10)
    Barrier of the conference on fire.
  - Paris gardé par le peuple, night of July 12 and 13, 1789 (Box 1, Page 11)
    Paris guarded by the people.
  - Pillage de la maison de St. Lazare, Monday, July 13, 1789 (Box 1, Page 12)
    Looting of the maison St. Lazare.
  - Pillage des armes au garde meuble, Monday, July 13, 1789 (Box 1, Page 13)
    Looting of weapons in storage.
  - Prise des armes aux Invalides, Morning of July 14, 1789 (Box 1, Page 14)
    Taking weapons from the Invalides.
  - Mort de M. de Flesselles prévôt des marchands de Paris, July 14, 1789 (Box 1, Page 15)
    Death of Mr. de Flesselles, mayor of Paris.
  - Prise de la Bastille, July 14, 1789 (Box 1, Page 16)
    Taking the Bastille.
  - Arrestation de Mr. De Launay, gouverneur de la Bastille, July 14, 1789 (Box 1, Page 17)
    Arrest of Mr. De Launay, governor of the Bastille.
  - Alerte de la nuit, July 14 and 15, 1789 (Box 1, Page 18)
    Alert the night.
  - Canons de Paris portes à Montmartre, July 15, 1789 (Box 1, Page 19)
    Parisian cannons taken to Montmartre.
  - Le roi arrivant à l'Hôtel-de-ville, July 17, 1789 (Box 1, Page 20)
    The King arrives at the Hotel-de-ville.
  - Supplice de Foulon à la Place de Grève, July 23, 1789 (Box 1, Page 21)
    Torture of Foulon at the Place de Grève.
  - Service funèbre des citoyens morts au siège de la Bastille, Discours prononce par l'abbé Fauchet, August 5, 1789 (Box 1, Page 22)
    Funeral service of the citizens killed in the siege of the Bastille, Speech delivered by the Abby Fauchet.
  - Bateau de poudre arrêté au Port St. Paul, August 6, 1789 (Box 1, Page 23)
    Gunpowder ship stopped at the Port of St. Paul.
  - Canons amenés de Chantilly à Paris, August 9, 1789 (Box 1, Page 24)
    Cannons brought from Chantilly to Paris.
  - Besenval conduit dans un vieux château fort, à Brie-Comte-Robert, August 10, 1789 (Box 1, Page 25)
    Besenval taken in the old castle-fortress, at Brie-Comte-Robert.
  - Offrandes faites à l'Assemblée Nationale par des dames artistes, September 7, 1789 (Box 1, Page 26)
    Offerings made to the National Assembly by women artists.
  - Bénédiction des drappeaux de la garde nationale Parisienne à Notre Dame, September 27, 1789 (Box 1, Page 27)
    Blessing the flag of the Parisian national guard at Notre Dame.
  - Orgie des gardes du corps dans la salle de l'opera de Versailles, October 1st, 1789 (Box 1, Page 28)
    Orgy of bodyguards in the opera hall of Versailles.
  - Les dames de la halle partant pour aller chercher le roi à Versailles, October 5, 1789 (Box 1, Page 29)
    Women of the market leave to go look for the King at Versailles.
  - Le roi promettant de venir à Paris avec sa famille, Salve d'Artillerie devant le Château de Versailles, October 6, 1789 (Box 1, Page 30)
    The King promises to come to Paris with his family, Salut of Arms before the Versailles castle.
  - Le roi arrivant à Paris avec sa famille, escorté de plus de trente mille âmes, October 6, 1789 (Box 1, Page 31)
    The King arrives in Paris with his family, escorted by more than thirty thousand souls.
  - Mr. la Fayette fait désarmer aux Champs Elisées deux cent soldats, January 12, 1790 (Box 1, Page 32)
    Mr. la Fayette has two hundred soldiers disarmed at the Champs-Elysées.
  - Le Commune de Paris décerne une épée et une couronne civique à C.J.W. Nesham anglais, January 15, 1790 (Box 1, Page 33)
    The commune of Paris bestows a sword of honor and civic crown to Englishman C.J.W. Nesham.
  - Les frères Agasse allant au supplice, leurs corps rendus à leur famille, February 8, 1790 (Box 1, Page 34)
    The brothers Agasse going to torture, their bodies returned to their family.
  - Pillage de l'arcenal de Lyon, February 7, 1790 (Box 1, Page 35)
    Pillage of the arsenal of Lyon.
  - Favras, faisant amende honorable en face de l'eglise de Notre Dame, à Paris, February 19, 1790 (Box 1, Page 36)
    Favras, does the honorable thing in front of the church Notre Dame, in Paris.
  - Massacre des patriotes de Montauban, May 10, 1790 (Box 1, Page 37)
    Massacre of patriots of Montauban.
  - Travaux du Champ de Mars, pour la fédération, July 14, 1790 (Box 1, Page 38)
    Work on the Champ de Mars, for the festival of the Federation.
  - Fédération générale faite à Paris, July 14, 1790 (Box 1, Page 39)
    Fédération générale made in Paris.
  - Fête exécutée en mémoire de la Fédération générale: Joute sur l'eau, July 18, 1790 (Box 1, Page 40)
    Celebration carried out in memory of the Fédération générale: Joust on the water.
  - Fêtes et illuminations aux Champs Elysées, July 18, 1790 (Box 1, Page 41)
    Festivities and illuminations at the Champs Elysées
  - Affaire de Nancy. Mort de Désille, August 31, 1790 (Box 1, Page 42)
    Nancy affaire. Death of Désille.
  - Pompe funèbre en l'honneur des citoyens soldats morts à Nancy, September 1790 (Box 1, Page 43)
    Funeral in honor of the citizen soldiers killed at Nancy.
  - Port de Brest. Insurrection des vaisseaux de Léopard et l'America, September 1790 (Box 1, Page 44)
    Port of Brest, insurrection of the vessels Leopard and America.
  - Le maire de Paris, allant au palais, poser les scélés sur les papiers du Parlement, November 1790 (Box 1, Page 45)
    The mayor of Paris, going to the palace, to put seals on the papers of Parliament.
  - Pillage de l'Hôtel de Castries, F.B.G. St. Germain à Paris, November 13, 1790 (Box 1, Page 46)
    Pillage of the Hotel de Castries, F.B.G. St. Germain in Paris.
  - Massacre à La Chapelle par les chasseurs des barriéres, January 1791 (Box 1, Page 47)
    Massacre at La Chapelle by the hunters barriers.
  - Affaire de Vincennes, February 28, 1791 (Box 1, Page 48)
    Vincennes affair.
  - Affaire des poignards dans l'intérieur du château des Tuileries, February 28, 1791 (Box 1, Page 49)
    Dagger affair inside the Tuileries castle.
  - Pompe funèbre de Mirabeau, April 4, 1791 (Box 1, Page 50)
    Mirabeau's funeral.
  - Manequin du Pape, brulé au Palais Royal, April 6, 1791 (Box 1, Page 51)
    Effigy of the Pope burned at the Palais Royal.
  - Entrées des barrières libres, May 1st, 1791 (Box 1, Page 52)
    Coming in by the open gate.
  - Arrestation de Louis Capet à Varennes, June 22, 1791 (Box 1, Page 53)
    The arrest of Louis Capet at Varennes.
  - Retour de Varennes. Arrivée de Louis Capet à Paris, June 25, 1791 (Box 1, Page 54)
    Return from Varennes. Arrival of Louis Capet in Paris.
  - Triomphe de Voltaire, July 11, 1791 (Box 1, Page 55)
    Triumph of Voltaire.
  - Publication de la loi martiale au Champ de Mars, July 17, 1791 (Box 1, Page 56)
    Publication of martial law on the Champ de Mars.
  - Proclamation de la constitution, Place du Marché des Innocens, September 14, 1791 (Box 1, Page 57)
    Proclamation of the Constitution, marketplace of the innocent.
  - Mort de l'escuyer dans l'eglise des Cordelliers à Avignon, October 16, 1791 (Box 1, Page 58)
    Death of a squire in the church of the Cordelliers in Avignon.
  - Premiere fête de la liberté a l'occasion des Suisses de château-vieux, April 15, 1792 (Box 1, Page 59)
    First festival of liberty at the Swiss château-vieux.
  - Mort du Général Dillon dans la ville de Lille, April 29, 1792 (Box 1, Page 60)
    Death of General Dillon in the city of Lille.
  - Pompe funèbre en l'honneur de Simoneau marie d'Éstampes, June 3, 1792 (Box 1, Page 61)
    Funeral procession in honor of Simoneau, mayor of Éstampes.
  - Le peuple entrant au château des Tuileries, June 20, 1792 (Box 1, Page 62)
    The people entering the Tuileries castle.
  - Commémoration de la prise de la Bastille, July 14, 1792 (Box 1, Page 63)
    Commemoration of the taking of the Bastille.
  - Prise du camp de Jalès par les patriotes, July 1792 (Box 1, Page 64)
    Taking the Jalès camp by the patriots.
  - Proclamation de la patrie en danger, July 22, 1792 (Box 1, Page 65)
    Proclamation of the country in danger.
  - Dîner des Marseillais au Champs-Élysées, July 30 1792 (Box 1, Page 66)
    Marseillais dinner on the Champs-Elysées.
  - Dix Août 1792. Siege et prise du château des Tuileries, August 10, 1792 (Box 1, Page 67)
    Siege and taking of the Tuileries castle.
  - Statue de Louis XIV abatue, Place des Victoires, August 11, 12, 13, 1792 (Box 1, Page 68)
    Statue of Louis XIV pulled down, Place des Victoires.
  - Translation de Louis Capet et de sa famille au temple, August 13, 1792 (Box 1, Page 69)
    Transfer of Louis Capet and his family to temple.
  - Émigration de La Fayette du camp devant Sedan, August 19, 1792 (Box 1, Page 70)
    Emigration of La Fayette from camp outside of Sedan.
  - Prise de Verdun, mort de Beaurepaire, September 2 ,1792 (Box 1, Page 71)
    Taking of Verdun, death of Beaurepaire.
  - Massacres des 2, 3, 4, 5 et 6 Septembre 1792, September 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6, 1792 (Box 1, Page 72)
    Massacres of September 2, 3, 4, 5, and 6, 1792.
  - Prise de la ville de Spire, September 29, 1792, or 7 Vendémiaire, Year One of the Republic (Box 1, Page 73)
    Taking of the town of Spire.
  - Bombardement de la ville de Lille, first days of October 1792, or 10, 11, 12 Vendemiaire, Year One of the Republic (Box 1, Page 74)
    Bombing of the town of Lille.
  - Victoire de Jemmapes, November 6, 1792, or 15 Brumaire Year One of the Republic (Box 1, Page 75)
    Victory of Jemmapes.
  - Assassinat de Basseville, à Rome, January 13, 1793, or 23 Nivôse Year One of the Republic (Box 1, Page 76)
    Assassination of Basseville, in Rome.
  - Assassinat de le Pelletier, Maison de Février restaurateur, January 20 1793, or 30 Nivôse Year One of the Republic (Box 1, Page 77)
    Assassination of le Pelletier, restaurant Maison de Février.
  - Supplice de Louis XVI, Place de la Révolution, January 21, 1793, or 1 Pluviôse Year One of the Republic (Box 1, Page 78)
    Torture of Louis XVI, Place de la Révolution.
  - Bataille de Nerwinde, March 18, 1793, or 28 Ventôse Year One of the Republic (Box 1, Page 79)
    Battle of Neerwinden.
  - Journées des 31 Mai 1er et 2 Juin 1793, 12, 13, and 14 Paririal Year One of the Republic (Box 1, Page 80)
    The days of May 31, June 1 and 2, 1793.